So, a new master class on AI coding was
just dropped by Google, and it is really
good. It's a highle overview of pretty
much everything that I teach on my
channel. In fact, a couple of people
actually sent this to me last week, and
they said, "Hey, Cole, this literally
looks like it could have been written by
you. It's the cleanest packaging I've
seen for everything that the industry is
converging on right now as far as best
practices and terminology for AI coding.
It's very well written, definitely worth
a read. So, I'll link to it in the
description, but it's also 51 pages
long, so it takes a while to get through
this, which is why I wanted to make this
video just to disseminate everything
nice and quickly for you. And even if
you're already pretty comfortable with
agentic engineering and AI coding, it's
worth going through this, right? The old
adage is you don't truly understand
something until you can teach it well.
So, it's important to take the instincts
you build over time and turn that into a
clear visualization, mental model, and
precise terminology. And so that's what
we really get with this on everything
the industry is converging on. And so
I've reordered things a little bit what
I'll show you here. I think there's a
better ordering than what they present.
But I want to go through this all with
you along with a diagram that I have
prepared and just give the good parts to
you really fast. So let's get into the
meat of it here. So the first big
question we have to answer here is what
the heck even is an SDLC? If you don't
come from a technical background, you're
probably not even familiar. And there's
the new phrase AIdriven SDLC. that's
being thrown around all of the time now.
So, it's short for software development
life cycle. And quite simply, it's the
process to go from idea all the way to
production. So, requirement gathering at
the start all the way to review,
deployment, and maintenance. And so,
it's a lot more than just writing the
code that sits in the middle. And with a
traditional SDLC, you spend a good few
days gathering requirements with your
stakeholder meetings and the product
manager creating the PRD, like all that
documentation upfront. And then you have
a couple of days of designing and then
the implementation is usually what would
take most of the time. The engineer
spending weeks writing the actual code
before you then go into the final steps
of testing, reviewing, deploying and
maintenance. And usually that would take
a week. Obviously, it depends a lot per
company. Just a general idea through uh
generalization here. And so now with the
AIdriven SDLC, the important thing here
is that everything we do up front and at
the very end, it's not actually that
much faster. Now the specification
quality is the new bottleneck. And that
is so true because there's so much that
still has to be human-driven with the
validation at the end and the
requirement gathering up front. And so
really, it's only what's in the middle
here. The implementation has gone from 1
to 3 weeks to minutes or hours with AI
coding assistance. The same thing is
dozens of times faster, especially
because agents can iterate with their
own system of tests and eval.
And so we have the bottleneck at the
start and at the end. I firmly believe
that a lot of the next $1 billion plus
companies are going to be platforms that
help speed up the requirements gathering
and the validation because we've solved
way more for what we have in the middle
now. And so that's why you hear so many
statistics around like AI coding
assistants 10xing the engineers output
but not actually 10xing the output of
the business is because we're
bottlenecked by other parts of software
engineering. Software engineering is a
lot more than just writing code. But the
thing is, as much as you can, you want
to remove implementation as the
bottleneck because that is still going
to save you a considerable amount of
time. And so doing that and just
generally making everything else in the
AIdriven SDLC as fast as possible is
what this article focuses on. And so
that brings us to the first thing that I
want to cover in the diagram. So I took
all the big long ideas from the article,
made it nice and concise for you here.
And so the first thing that they talk
about is that AI coding is a spectrum,
not a switch. And I really appreciate
that because most people think of it as
something that's binary. Either you're
vibe coding or you're doing agentic
engineering. But it is a spectrum
depending on the level of your system.
And so we'll talk about the system and
the harness in a bit. But vibe coding is
where you send in a prompt without much
planning. And then your validation is,
hey, does it seem like it work? Right?
like you'll test the application a
little bit uh and then you'll just move
on to the next iteration. With
structured AI assisted, we have more
detailed prompts. We're doing more
spot-checking and then we get all the
way to aentic engineering where we have
a entire engineered set of resources and
workflows for our AI coding assistant
with specs and automated evals and CI
gates. So, the agent has a way to really
iterate and figure out things that go
wrong before you have to correct it.
This is where the real power comes in.
And so it's not like we always need
agentic engineering. Sometimes vibe
coding is actually enough for proof of
concepts or you just want to create an
MVP. I used to just always dismiss vibe
coding. But I think there is genuinely a
place for it. And so the spectrum Google
is saying is not just like you're
evolving yourself. It's you pick the
right one for the job. It's just agentic
engineering is usually where you want to
be because this is where you're really
creating reliable code. And in the
article, Google also has this table that
I really appreciate. It makes things
nice and concrete. So for each level,
what does it look like for these
different dimensions? And so for intense
specification, for example, which is
just how do you communicate upfront what
you want. For vibe coding, it's just
casual natural language prompts. So
you're just describing at a very high
level what you're looking for. With
structured AI assisted coding, the
middle of the spectrum, you're getting
more detail, but you still don't really
have a workflow for creating formal
specs, architecture docs, like when you
get to aentic engineering, this is where
you really have a repeatable process and
you have specifications that are
actually engineered just like the code.
And then for verification, like we
covered this a little bit already, but
for Vive coding, it's more does it just
seem to work. You're not doing much of a
deep dive at all. With structured AI
system coding, you're getting a little
bit into it with more manual testing and
spa-checking of the code maybe. And then
for agentic engineering, this is where
you have the whole process for the agent
to iterate itself with tests and CI/CD
gates. Also, LLM judges, you have a
separate code review process for
yourself and another agent. And I don't
need to cover everything here, but
getting down to the risk profile with
vibe coding, it's high, right? like
acceptable for disposable code like I
was saying earlier but then if you
really want the most reliable code
possible that's where you want
systematic verification at every stage
that comes with aentic engineering okay
so if aentic engineering is the way to
go most of the time how do we actually
do it like what separates aentic
engineering from vibe coding and really
everything can be wrapped up in the
harness so the harness is the set of
context rules tools and workflows that
you bring into the AI coding assistant.
It's the layer that you control. And the
big thing that Google is claiming here
is that the large language model that
you use for your AI coding assistant is
only 10% of the system or it only
matters 10%.
Everything else like your instructions
and tools and context and guardrails and
orchestration and observability like
there's so much here that makes up the
other 90%. And that's actually a really
good thing because the model is what we
don't control. The harness is what we
get to create for our specific code
bases, architectures, and tech stacks.
And it really is true that the industry
is converging on a lot of these things.
Like we have this article from Anthropic
that I covered a couple of weeks ago on
my channel, just best practices for
using cloud code in general. And one of
the headlines that they have here is
that the harness matters as much as the
model. And so now Google and myself as
well were taking this even further to
say not only does it matter as much but
it actually matters more than the model.
Like the model only being 10%. Clearly
Google is like okay you need to put your
focus on the rest of the harness here.
And they also have a very similar
definition of what goes into the
harness. So cloud code right here they
say it's your global rules. It's your
hooks like the deterministic actions you
want in your life cycle your skills. So,
the workflows that you have packaged up,
uh, your ways that you search your
codebase, the MCP servers, and your sub
aents, like these are all of the
primitives, as I call them, for working
with literally any AI coding assistant.
And if we go now into Google's article
here, they say the agent is the model
plus the harness. And they have this
diagram that lays out exactly everything
that goes into the harness. And you can
see this is where I got the numbers, by
the way. So, the model being 10%. So you
have the large language model in the
middle still matters to an extent
because it is the brain. It is the
reasoning in your system but everything
else around it is a huge deal. So you
have your instructions MCP servers
guardrails and hooks. I mean everything
is the exact same as what anthropic
presented in their article. And then the
layer above is where you have all of the
testing infrastructure. So the eval
to iterate itself. And then the top
layer is more for you and for
production. So the observability and
tracing, the scaling, right? Like that's
pretty important when you want to take
anything an AI coding assistant produces
and actually take it all the way to
production. The sponsor of today's video
is Better DB, a self-tuning Valky/Ris
caching and observability platform for
AI agents, and it is open-source. So,
we're talking all about the AI SDLC in
this video, but not covering that much
tools we can use to help us with
reliability and monitoring in
production, that end stage of the SDLC.
And better DB is a fantastic example of
an AI native tool that can help us with
this. So, monitoring our database in
production, using our AI coding
assistant with it to suggest changes and
improvements based on live production
data, and a semantic cache to help us
scale our database. Let me show you how
these things work really quick. My
favorite part of Better DB is the
semantic cache. Take a look at this.
You'll see how it works very quickly. If
I ask what's the capital of France, it's
not in my Better DB cache yet, so it's a
miss. And it calls a model to get the
answer. But the next time I ask
something that is similar, we get a
cache hit. It doesn't even have to be
the exact same wording because it's
semantic similarity search like
traditional rags. So, we get a much
faster answer. And we have an MCP server
so we can connect our AI coding
assistance directly to our better DB
cache. So we can ask how it's doing. We
can have it suggest improvements and
even make those directly. So it's very
easy to improve our system over time
with the help of AI. And then also we
have a dashboard to monitor everything.
So we can see how our agent and our
cache is performing in production with
real user data. And the best part is
better DB is open source and free to get
started. So I'll have a link in the
description. I'd highly recommend them
as a tool to help you scale manage your
costs for agents you're deploying to
production. And so now Google is saying
with harness engineering we have the
idea of the factory. So instead of the
engineer writing the code or the product
manager writing the PRD by hand, instead
we are responsible for designing the
system, creating the harness and then
the agent is the one that is actually
producing our code and documentation.
And so this is more of an investment
upfront than vibe coding because we have
to create the specs and guardrails, but
then we use that to then go into this
repeatable system of we plan with the
agent, we have it build, and then we
have our quality gates at the end for
testing and evaling with an iterative
loop here for the agent to improve its
output autonomously and then get to the
point where we have something for us to
review and ship. And so this entire
thing, we want to delegate all of the
coding to the AI coding assistant. Even
with agentic engineering, you are
delegating all of the coding. So this is
not a spectrum of how much do we write
by hand versus trust the agent. It is
just a spectrum of how evolved of a
system do we actually have here. So
Google does get a little bit repetitive
here because when they talk about the
factory model for the first time and
what goes into it, it's really the same
thing as what goes into building a
harness or the AI layer they already
talked about. So it's your your context
and rules, your test and quality gates,
your workflows, your guardrails and your
hooks, right? They have a really good
visualization for where the developer
actually stands in the process. Now, so
we define our specs, context, and
requirements up front and you use those
specs for your planning agent. So every
single time you build anything with an
AI coding assistant when you're doing
agentic engineering is you're going to
have one agent that does the plan for
the bug fix, for the new feature,
whatever it is. And then the guard rails
that you design and like the sandboxed
environment, that is what's going to be
used by the actual coding agent. But
it's important here that you do split
this into two separate sessions because
your planning agent is going to build up
a lot of context. You want to avoid
context rod and it's going to build up a
lot of bias. And so you take the plan as
an artifact. You send that into the
coding agent and then you do your test
and verification and iterate there. And
this is also where we can come in the
loop to review and approve things
ourselves because you definitely fall
more into vibe coding if you're not
reviewing the output yourself. Even if
you do have quite an autonomous system,
right? Like even if it's just that pull
request at the end for agentic
engineering, generally you want a human
to be reviewing that before you mark it
as pass and you go on to the rest of the
process for deployment to production.
And throughout this entire workflow,
that's where we have our guardrails like
token limits and security policies,
everything that you are engineering
upfront. And the really cool thing about
this whole system is that we can make it
better over time. Just like we evolve
our codebase over time, we can evolve
our system. So I I call this the system
evolution mindset. Whenever you
encounter an issue with your AI coding
assistant, like something comes up here
where it has to iterate more than you
would want or you have to step in before
you ship, instead of just fixing the bug
and moving on, you actually talk to your
coding agent like you have it do some
retrospection and say, "Hey, where could
we make our workflows or our rules like
any part of our AI layer better so that
issue is less likely to come up again?"
And so that way every single time you go
through this process over and over and
over again, you're making it more and
more reliable. And the harness is worth
investing your time into. Like it it
really is the 90%. I mean, there's a lot
of studies that are done like terminal
bench 2.0. It's one of the biggest
benchmarks we have out there. Like every
single time a new model comes out, this
is one of the percentages that you see.
There's a lot of studies done where like
they were able to take a model from
outside the top 30 into the top five
just by creating an AI layer of rules
and workflows for it to run through the
things you usually test for the
benchmark. Lane chain was able to
increase it 13.7 points. Like that's the
difference between Sonnet and Opus. Like
you can make sonnet work as well as Opus
if you have the right system, the right
process that you're having it go through
as the harness. So if the harness is the
most important part of agentic
engineering, then it's clear that the
most important skill within that is how
do we engineer each of the individual
components of the harness like our
rules, workflows, and a guard rails. And
so we've covered the different
components already, but a key
delineation that Google makes here that
I really like is the static context
versus dynamic context. And this is
really important because it's all about
context management. Context is your most
precious resource when working with AI
coding assistants, both for the sake of
cost and avoiding context rot. We don't
want to fill the window of our LLM, our
coding agent, too much because LLMs get
overwhelmed with information just like
people do. And so nice visualization
here. They talk about what goes into
static versus dynamic. So static context
is things like your rules and core
guardrails, the system prompt. It's
loaded into the coding agent session
guaranteed every single time. time. That
makes it reliable because the agent
doesn't have to seek out this
information, but it's expensive because
you're filling the context window up
front. And so, it's important to have at
least some rules and guard rails up
front, but you want to make them very
lean. And then everything else goes in
dynamic context so it's efficient and
scalable because it's information that
the agent has to actually seek out. Like
you might have an an agent skill for
planning like it loads that skill when
you want it to do the planning workflow
or you have conventions for a part of
the codebase you want it to load when it
operates on that part of the codebase
and so it's very scalable so you're not
shoving it into the context up front but
the risk there is the agent might not
grab for that context when it should
like it might not load the skill or
perform the rag search when you would
hope it to or when it would be optimal
to do so. But large language models are
getting better and better at relying on
dynamic context and loading it when it
should. And so like agent skills are
becoming very very important right now,
right? So they say rather than embedding
every piece of specialized knowledge
into the agent system prompt, skills
allow the agent to remain a lightweight
generalist that flexes into specialist
roles on demand through progressive
disclosure. And this is so important
because the underlying lesson here is
that we really only need one agent for
everything and then we can make it
specialized with our skills, i.e. our
workflows. And so something that people
used to do way too much before is they
would have these really complicated
multi- aent systems with all these
specialists or they use a ton of these
specialized sub aents they would create.
And really the industry is moving away
from that because we can just have one
generalist agent that we make specific
with the skills that we have at load.
Like we can have it become a code
reviewer or become a planner. That
session can turn into the specialization
that you need thanks to dynamic context.
So keep it simple. You really only need
one agent to drive most of your agentic
engineering. Okay. So the article has
been very valuepacked already. There's
just two more things that I want to
cover with you here. I want to talk
about your role as the conductor and
orchestrator and then also the token
economics. And so an interesting thing
that Google presents here is the idea of
you as the engineer are going to move
between two modes as you're using your
AI coding assistant. And so the
conductor is more how we used AI coding
assistants when generative AI was first
a thing. Like we had our tab complete.
We're still steering every move, working
in individual files. That's the
conductor. The orchestrator is a lot of
what people have been focusing on more
recently where we have a coding agent
handling much larger tasks spanning
entire code bases, maybe even multiple
code bases. We're reviewing the outcomes
instead of changes to individual files.
We have agents running in parallel.
We're really scaling our output with AI
coding assistance here. And almost
everybody is focusing entirely on this.
And this this is like the one part of
the article I don't know if I agree with
Google because they're saying that you
actually want to move between both. Like
there's still a time and place to be
micromanaging the AI coding assistant at
a single file level. Honestly, I don't
know if I agree with this. I think when
you build the harness to be reliable
enough and you're confident in your
rules and workflows, you can always live
at this level. But they do make some
interesting arguments where it's like
any kind of like deeper debugging you
have to do or just initial exploration
like you are going to get very granular
with the coding agent because that's the
times where you might need to really be
in the loop and guide it. So I think
there's a time and place for it but I
feel like when you have the right system
and it's working well for you, you don't
really like you kind of graduate from
being the conductor. I don't think
you're always moving between the two.
But it is an interesting idea you know
especially as an organization when you
have a lot of traditional engineers and
you're first getting into aentic
engineering I think it is good to have
this mental model just until you have
the system developed where you'd
graduate to only ever staying here.
Cool. And then the very last thing that
I want to cover here is the token
economics. I really love how they frame
things here. So, like we said, vibe
coding, you don't always want to avoid
it, but there is a big cost that comes
if you lean on it too much because at
first when you're first adopting AI
coding assistance for yourself or a
company, Vive coding is going to be
cheaper. It's lower capital expenditure
because you don't have to dedicate
yourself or a team to design the initial
harness. But the problem is it's very
high operational expenditure because you
start burning through millions and
millions of tokens iterating on slop
code because you don't have a system for
your AI coding assistant to follow your
workflow and your conventions. And so
agentic engineering it has that high
capital expenditure because you have to
dedicate your time up front or you have
to like in a larger organization usually
you create a smaller forward deployed
engineer team to build up that harness
to then scale to the entire
organization. So you're dedicating
manpower to build something initially,
but then it scales extremely well
because the output of your AI coding
assistants are better and better and
better over time and you have that
grounding in a system that you just
build once upfront and evolve over time.
So high capital expenditure but then low
operational expenditure and you know you
have that crossover that you reach
extremely quickly like you want to just
take the dive and build that system up
front because yeah you're going to get
to the point where agentic engineering
is three to 10 times more reliable and
cheaper than vibe coding because you're
not burning through millions of tokens.
So there you go. That is everything you
need to know at a high level for the new
AIdriven software development life
cycle. It is worth building that harness
and investing in it. It is an engineered
resource that lives in version control
just like the code itself. So, I hope
that you found this useful. Let me know
in the comments what kinds of content
you want me to create to expand on any
of these ideas here cuz this is my bread
and butter. If you appreciated this
video, you're looking forward to more
things on Agentic Engineering, I would
really appreciate a like and a
subscribe. And with that, I will see you
in the next video.